Translator's note
One has to be serious.
It's only those who are really vitally serious
can live properly, can live...
اللي
that is complete and whole.
And that seriousness doesn't exclude joy,
enjoyment.
But as long as there is fear,
one cannot possibly be serious, or enjoy,
or know what it means to have great joy.
And fear seems to be one
of the most common things in life.
And strangely, we have accepted it.
As a way of life.
As we have accepted violence in all its various forms,
as a way of life,
we have also accepted and have got used to
being psychologically as well as physically afraid.
And
this evening, if we can,
we should go into this question.
We should, I feel,
go into it so completely
that we understand it
so fully
that when we leave the hall or this place,
we shall be rid of this fear.
I think it can be done.
It isn't just a theory
or a hope.
But
if one gives,
as we share presently,
complete attention to this question of fear,
I am quite sure
that
in exploring
the causes of fear
and also
how to approach it,
how to look at it,
how to completely end it.
So that our mind,
the human mind that has suffered so much,
that has endured so much pain,
that has lived with great sorrow and fear,
such a mind
can
completely be free of this thing called fear.
And to understand it,
we must communicate with each other quite easily.
Communication implies,
the very word,
means creating together,
understanding together,
working together.
Not that you,
merely
listen to the speaker,
hear a few words or ideas,
but
with the speaker
take a journey
together
and understand
this very complex problem
of the mind,
of this spiritual Hemat навер,
which I am talking about,
can be
pleased,
strong,
and
very 적lebrious.
قفّيا
And to communicate, to take this journey together,
implies neither acceptance nor denial.
Not saying to oneself,
it is absolutely impossible to be rid of fear,
or rationalise fear,
or accept it.
You need a free mind to enquire into this question,
a mind that has no conclusion,
that doesn't say it is
possible or it is not possible,
because we are enquiring, exploring together.
So you must be free to observe, to enquire,
to understand, to understand.
And that is absolutely essential,
so that one has no prejudice to find out,
prejudice which will prevent
from the understanding of the truth of what is.
You see, there are so many forms of fear.
Yes.
Both physical as well as psychological,
psychosomatic fears.
And to go into each one
of these various forms of fear
requires enormous time, demands a great many days,
to go into every aspect of every fear.
Yes.
But I think one can observe the quality of fear,
the general fear, not a particular fear.
Yes.
Observe the nature of fear,
the nature of the fear,
the nature of the fear, the fear
of the fear, the fear of the fear.
The structure of fear, the structure of fear.
Not get lost in a detail
or in a particular form of one's own fear.
Yes.
Because when we understand the nature
and the structure of fear,
then we can.
Then apply that understanding
or come with that understanding or approach
with that understanding of a particular fear.
One may be afraid of the dark, physically.
Or one may be afraid of one's wife or husband.
Or what the public says or thinks.
Or what the public says or thinks or does.
Or one may be afraid of this sense of loneliness.
Or the emptiness of life,
the boredom of a meaningless existence
that one leads.
Or one may be afraid of the future,
the tomorrow, the uncertainty,
the insecurity, the bomb.
Or one may be afraid of death.
The ending of one's life.
So there are various forms of fear.
Neurotic, as well as sane, rational fears.
If fear can ever be rational or sane.
But most of us, apparently,
are neurotically afraid
of both the past,
of today and of tomorrow.
The things that one has done in the past.
Or the ill health that
one has had in the past
with all its pain and agony,
and not wanting it repeated.
And is one afraid of that, tomorrow?
One is afraid of time.
Growing old, getting senile,
depending on another.
So there is,
fear of time,
fear of the past and of the future.
And this fear of loneliness,
of death,
of public opinion,
of not conforming,
not being able to succeed,
not being able to fulfil,
not being somebody in this stupid world,
and so on.
And there are so many fears.
Not only conscious fears,
fears that one is aware of,
but also there are fears,
deep down,
undiscovered, unexplored,
in the deep recesses of one's own mind.
So the question is,
not only how to deal with the conscious fears,
as well as those that are hidden,
the fear of time,
and the fear of the future.
That is,
yesterday,
of the things that one has done,
the repetition of that misery,
of tomorrow,
the uncertainty,
the insecurity,
both psychological as well as physical.
And there are the fears of great loneliness,
and the escape from that loneliness.
Surely,
fear is a movement
away from what is.
The flight,
the escape,
the avoidance
of actually what is,
the movement,
the flight away,
brings about fear.
That is,
when there is comparison
of any kind,
it breeds fear.
Comparing oneself with another,
whom you think is greater,
wiser,
nobler,
etc., etc.,
and the comparison
of what you are with what you should be.
So,
fear
is a movement away from the actual,
the what is,
the movement,
not the object to which you escape.
And fear
comes about through comparison.
And there are,
there is the fear
deeply hidden in oneself,
of which one is not aware.
So there are these problems,
and all very complex.
And none of these problems
of fear
can be resolved through will.
Saying to oneself,
I will not be afraid.
And the act of will has no meaning.
I hope you are following all this.
It isn't a game I am playing
with you,
nor you playing a game with me.
We are considering a very serious problem.
And I hope you understand.
And therefore you have to give
your attention to it.
And you cannot give attention
if you are interpreting or translating
or comparing with what is being said
with what you already know.
You have to listen.
And the art of listening
is to be able to understand.
One has to learn.
Because one doesn't listen at all.
One is always comparing,
evaluating, judging,
denying.
Therefore one prevents,
you prevent yourself from actually listening.
To listen so completely to another
implies that you give your whole attention.
Which doesn't mean you agree or disagree.
Because there is no agreement or disagreement
when we are exploring together.
Only
the microscope through which you look
may be dull,
may not be clear.
So if you have a precision instrument
then what you see
is what another will also see.
Therefore there is no question
of agreement or disagreement or denial.
So,
we are trying to examine
this whole question of fear.
So you will have to give your attention
because it is your life.
Because fear
deadens the mind,
makes the mind insensitive,
dull.
How can a mind that is afraid love?
A mind that depends.
What can it know
of joy except fear?
So,
there are
conscious as well as
hidden fears.
How do you
first enquire?
How do you expose
those hidden fears?
And when you do expose them,
how will you be free of them?
How can the mind be free of them?
That is the first question.
Please do
follow this.
You yourself are doing it.
You yourself are observing it.
The speaker is only pointing out.
Is it...
How does it happen
that the hidden fears are opened,
exposed?
One can know
the conscious fears
and how to deal with them will come
presently.
But there are the hidden fears
perhaps much more important.
So how will you deal with them?
How will you expose them?
Would you permit me to take my coat off?
You don't mind?
So we are considering
how the
deep layers of fears, hidden,
can be exposed.
Can they be exposed through analysis?
Analysing them,
seeing their causes.
Will analysis
free the mind from fear?
Not a particular neurotic fear,
but the whole fear,
the whole structure of fear.
Analysis.
In analysis is implied
not only time,
taking many, many, many days, years,
whole of one's life,
at the end of it perhaps
you may understand little
but you are ready for the grave.
And also
in analysis implies
the analyser.
Who is the analyser?
Is he the professional,
the expert?
Who has a degree,
going to analyse
your deep,
hidden fears?
And he will also take time.
And therefore also your money.
So analysis
implies
the analyser,
who is the censor,
who is the result
of many forms of conditioning,
and he is going to analyse
the fear
which he himself has created.
Right?
I hope you are following all this.
Because our intention is
that when you do leave
this rather warm hall
that you no longer
have any form of fear.
It can be done.
And you will know
quite a different kind of life.
You will know what
tremendous joy is.
A mind that is completely
free of this
terrible thing called fear.
And to be free of that
you have to...
We together are going to
walk together.
You are going to work as hard
as the speaker is working.
So analysis
implies time
and analyser.
Please see
the truth of this.
Not your opinion
as opposed to the speaker's opinion
or somebody else's opinion
or knowledge.
See the truth of it.
That it takes time.
And
the interval
between
that which
you are analysing
and the ending of that
will involve
time
and therefore
many other factors
which
give it
a different direction.
The analyser
is
a fragment
among many other fragments
which go to make up
the me,
the I,
the ego.
And
the analyser
is
the
me.
So he
becomes
the analyser,
assumes
the authority
of the analyser.
And his
analysis
must be
complete
each time.
Otherwise
what's the point
of analysis
at all?
So analysis
which implies
time
and division
is not
the ending
of fear.
Is this somewhat clear?
To see this means
that you have
completely
put aside
the whole idea
of progressive change.
Because the very
factor of change
is
one of the major
causes of fear.
Are you all being
mesmerised?
Because
to me
to the speaker
they say,
this is a very important thing,
therefore he feels
very strongly.
He speaks intensely.
He is not doing propaganda.
There is nothing to join
for you to join.
Nothing for you to believe.
But
to observe
and
learn
and be free
of this fear.
So analysis
is not the way.
You understand
what that means
when you see
the truth of that?
It means
that
you are no longer
thinking
in terms
of the analyser
who is going to examine,
who is going to analyse,
who is going to judge,
evaluate.
Therefore
your mind is
free of a particular
burden called analysis.
Therefore it is capable
of looking
directly
directly.
And
if analysis
is not the way
and therefore
false,
then
it is not the way.
How are you to look
at this fear?
How are you to
bring out
all the
structure,
all the hidden parts
of fear?
Through dreams?
Dreams
are the continuation
of waking
hours.
Through sleep.
Aren't they?
Are you following
all this?
I don't know
if you have observed
that in dreams
there is always action.
Doing something
or happening something.
Something is happening.
Which is the same
in the waking hours.
A continuation
of the waking hours
when there is sleep
through dreams
is still part
of the whole movement.
So,
dreams
have no value.
Are you accepting
all this?
Great Scott.
I hope.
I am sure you don't
but it doesn't matter.
Because you see
what is happening.
We are eliminating
the things
to which you are
accustomed.
Analysis,
dreams,
will,
time,
and the mind.
So,
when you eliminate
the mind becomes
extraordinarily sensitive.
And
through this elimination
it has become
not only sensitive
but intelligent.
Now,
with that sensitivity
and intelligence
we are going to look
at fear.
Right?
Are we going together?
You know,
this is great fun
if you really go into this.
Because then
you turn away,
you turn your back
on the whole of
the social
structure
in which
time,
analysis,
will
is in operation.
So, what is fear?
Right?
What is fear?
How does it come?
Fear is always
in relation
to something.
It doesn't exist
by itself.
In relation
to something
that is permanent
to another thing
that is also permanent.
Right?
There is fear
of what happened yesterday,
the repetition
of that tomorrow,
whether it is pain
or some other form,
there is always
a fixed point
from which
relationship takes place.
But fear
is not
a sign
of what is happening
today.
It is a sign
of what is happening
now.
And there are
many things
that are
happening
now.
And
fear
is it
in the
physical
or
in the
physical
sense
of
what
is
happening
and
what
it
related to the past, the memory of the past pain,
and not wanting the repetition
of that pain tomorrow or today,
in relation to something that has happened.
And what is fear?
You have had pain yesterday.
That's obvious, you have had it.
Or there is some hope
tomorrow which might not come about.
So there is fear of
yesterday, there is fear of tomorrow.
How does that fear come about?
Right?
You are asking the question, not I.
So you are working hard.
I have had pain yesterday, obviously,
and
there is the memory of it,
not wanting it again tomorrow.
How does fear come into this?
Thinking about the pain of yesterday,
thinking,
the memory,
of yesterday's pain,
projects the fear of tomorrow,
of having pain again tomorrow.
So thought brings about fear.
Right?
No?
You are following this?
Thought.
Thought brings about fear, breeds fear,
and also thought cultivates pleasure.
To understand fear, you must also understand pleasure,
because they are interrelated.
Without understanding one, you can't understand the other.
Which is, you can't say, I must have only pleasure,
and no fear.
Because fear is the other side of the coin
which is called pleasure.
Right?
We are following each other?
So, there was pleasure yesterday,
sexual or different kinds of pleasures,
you think about it,
the image,
through the curd of pleasure,
which is thinking about it.
And you may not have it tomorrow.
So thought
engenders fear.
Right?
I think that's fairly clear, isn't it?
So thought not only sustains pleasure,
also nourishes fear.
And thought has separated itself
as the analyser.
The thing to be analysed is also part of thought.
So it is playing tricks upon itself.
So then the question is,
if thought is doing all this,
thought that refuses to examine
the hidden unconscious fears,
the thought that has set up,
set the analyser separate from the thing to be analysed,
thought that has brought in time
as a means of escaping fear,
but sustaining fear,
and thought also nourishing pleasure,
which has nothing whatsoever to do with joy.
Because joy is not the product of thought.
It is not pleasure.
You can cultivate pleasure,
you can think about it endlessly,
and derive great pleasure,
but you can't do that with joy.
The moment you do that, it has gone.
It has become something from which you derive pleasure,
and therefore which you are afraid to lose.
So thought,
is responsible
for both pleasure,
pain, fear.
And also thought is afraid
of being completely lonely.
Thought has already condemned it.
And so thought invents a way of escaping
from that loneliness
through various forms of religious entertainments,
or cultural something or other.
The everlasting search for
deeper and wider dependencies.
So thought is responsible.
Then what is one to do?
You understand all this, I hope.
What is one to do
when one realises
that thought,
which is a response of memory
to any challenge,
minor or major,
which sustains both pleasure and fear,
these are all facts,
not the speaker's invention
or his peculiar philosophy
or theory.
These are absolute, daily, observable facts
which are not just
a matter of time.
They are also observable facts.
Then the next question is,
what is one to do?
There is thought.
You can't kill it.
You can't destroy it.
You can't say, I'll forget it.
You can't resist it.
If you do,
that's another form of thought.
Thought is the response of memory.
And you need that memory
to function daily,
to go to your office,
to go to your home,
to be able to talk.
Memory is the storehouse
of your technological knowledge.
So you need memory,
completely.
And also you see
how memory
sustains fear
through thought.
Having had pleasure yesterday,
seeing the beauty of that lovely sunset,
and you want that again repeated,
that same experience,
either through drug
or through going to that particular spot
to look at that exquisite light.
And when it doesn't happen,
there is pain, disappointment,
frustration.
So thought.
You need memory
with all the purity and clarity
of thought
in one direction,
technologically,
to function daily,
to earn a livelihood and so on.
And also
you see there is
the fact
that thought also breeds fear.
That thought also breeds fear.
So what is one to do?
What is the mind to do?
You have understood the question?
Is it clear?
You are putting the question
to yourself
I am not putting the question to you.
If you are
accepting my question,
the speaker's question,
then it is not your question.
If it is your question,
and which it must be
after this examination,
if it is not, you are asleep.
If it is your own,
then how will you answer it?
How will you answer this question
after having gone through
the various facts
of analysis,
of time,
of escape,
of dependency?
See that a movement away from what is,
is fear,
the movement itself is fear.
After observing all that,
seeing the truth of all that,
not opinion,
not your casual judgement,
what is your answer
to this question?
That thought must function
most efficiently,
sanely,
and yet that very thought
becomes a danger,
because it breeds fear.
Now, before you answer that question,
what is the state of the mind
that has gone through all this?
You understand what I mean?
What is the state of the mind
that has gone through all this?
What is the state of the understanding
of your mind,
the mind that has examined
all the various forms
which have been exposed,
which has been explained or observed?
What is the quality of your mind now?
Because on that quality
you are going to answer.
Right?
If you have not taken the journey,
you have no answer.
But if you have actually
taken the journey,
step by step,
and gone into everything
that we have discussed,
then your mind, you will see,
has become extraordinarily intelligent,
alive, sensitive,
because they have thrown off
all the burdens
that it has accumulated.
Then,
the question is,
how do you observe
this whole process of thinking?
Is there a centre from which you think?
Do follow all this, please.
The centre being as the censor,
the one who judges,
evaluates,
condemns, justifies.
Do you still think from that centre?
Or,
there is no centre from which
you think at all.
But you think.
Right?
You see the difference?
Is this all getting too much?
Or do tell me, please.
No.
No?
I'm surprised.
You are merely listening,
I'm afraid.
Look, sir,
thought has created a centre
as the me.
And I'm not saying
you should be ashamed,
but in reality,
you are a self.
You are a self.
You are.
And you are the self.
So,
you are the self.
You are the self.
as the me.
Me, my opinions, my country, my God, my experience,
my house, my furniture, my wife, my children, my country,
you know, me, me, me.
That is the centre from which you act, think.
That centre divides.
And because of that centre and that division
there must be conflict, obviously.
When it is your opinion against somebody else's opinion,
my country and your country, you know, all that, division.
Which means the centre is always dividing.
And if you think from that centre
and observe from that centre fear,
you are still caught in fear.
Because that centre has separated itself
from the thing it has called fear.
And therefore it says, I must get rid of it,
I must analyse it,
I must overcome it, resist it, and so on.
So you are strengthening fear.
So can you look, can the mind look at fear
– which we are going
to a little bit more –
without the centre?
Can you look at that fear without naming it?
Because the moment you say fear,
it is already in the past,
because you have named it.
You are following all this?
Because the moment you name something,
don't you divide it?
The white and the black
and the brown and the communist,
don't you?
And so that very division
is a form of resistance,
conflict and fear.
So the question is to observe
without that centre,
and not to name the
thing called fear as it arises.
All this requires tremendous discipline.
You know, the word discipline means to learn,
to learn from somebody.
You are not learning from the speaker,
you are learning from yourself.
And to observe all this very closely,
with care,
which means with affection and attention,
then the mind is looking without the division
as a centre to which it has been accustomed to.
Therefore there is an ending of fear,
both the hidden and the open.
If you haven't done it this evening,
don't take it home and think about it.
Truth is something that you must say immediately.
And to say something clearly and immediately,
you must give your heart and your mind
and your whole being.
That's all.
Thank you.